When you wish upon a star, your dreams come true.
Pinocchio is a animation, family, fantasy film directed by Hamilton Luske.
When the gentle woodcarver Geppetto builds a marionette to be his
substitute son, a benevolent fairy brings the toy to life.
The puppet, named Pinocchio, is not yet a human boy.
He must earn the right to be real by proving that he
is brave, truthful, and unselfish.
Pinocchio / Alexander (voice) (uncredited), played by Dickie Jones.
Jiminy Cricket (voice) (uncredited), played by Cliff Edwards.
Geppetto (voice) (uncredited), played by Christian Rub.
The Blue Fairy (voice) (uncredited), played by Evelyn Venable.
'Honest John' Worthington Foulfellow (voice)
(uncredited), played by Walter Catlett.
Gideon (hiccup) (voice) (uncredited), played by Mel Blanc.
Pinocchio is a 1940 American animated musical fantasy film loosely based on Carlo Collodi's 1883 novel
The Adventures of Pinocchio, produced by Walt Disney and released by RKO Radio Pictures.
The production was supervised by Ben Sharpsteen and Hamilton Luske, and the film's sequences were
directed by Bill Roberts, Norman Ferguson, Jack Kinney, Wilfred Jackson and T.
With the voices of Cliff Edwards, Dickie Jones, Christian Rub, Walter Catlett, Charles Judels, Evelyn Venable,  Frankie Darro, Mel Blanc and Clarence
Nash, the film follows a wooden puppet, Pinocchio, who is created by an old woodcarver, Geppetto, and brought to life by a blue fairy.
Wishing to become a real boy, Pinocchio must prove himself to be "brave, truthful, and unselfish." Along his journey, Pinocchio encounters several characters representing the
temptations and consequences of wrongdoing, as a cricket named Jiminy, who takes the role of Pinocchio's conscience, attempts to guide him in matters of right and wrong.
Pinocchio was a groundbreaking achievement in the area of effects animation, giving realistic movement to
vehicles and machinery as well as natural elements such as rain, water, lightning, smoke, and shadow.
After premiering at the Center Theatre in New York City on February 7,
1940, Pinocchio was released in theatres on February 23, 1940.
Although it received critical acclaim and became the first animated feature to win a competitive Academy Award — winning two for Best Music, Original Score and for Best Music, Original Song for "When You Wish Upon a
Star" (the latter that would later serve as the Walt Disney Company's signature song) — it was initially a commercial failure, mainly due to World War II cutting off the European and Asian markets.
It eventually made a profit after its 1945 rerelease, and is considered one of the greatest
animated films ever made, with a 100% rating on the website Rotten Tomatoes.
The film and characters are still prevalent in popular culture, featuring
at various Disney parks and other forms of entertainment.
In 1994, Pinocchio was added to the United States National Film Registry for being deemed "culturally, historically, or aesthetically
significant."
In 2000, a live-action musical television film titled Geppetto was released with some elements from the 1940 film.
A live-action remake of the same title directed by Robert
Zemeckis was released in 2022 on Disney+.
The film explores themes of rescue, sea, child
abuse, based on novel or book, magic.